<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>This is for all you the inhabitants of Whitewell to consider, who deny the perfect life of Christ to be brought forth in his people here upon earth, and manifested in their mortal flesh by a ceasing from sin. And to all others whom it may concern.</title>
            <author>Bradly, Richard, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4125A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578176</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2615:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>This is for all you the inhabitants of Whitewell to consider, who deny the perfect life of Christ to be brought forth in his people here upon earth, and manifested in their mortal flesh by a ceasing from sin. And to all others whom it may concern.</title>
                  <author>Bradly, Richard, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Rich. Bradly.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inner Light.</term>
               <term>Repentance.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172131:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>This is for all you the Inhabitants of <hi>Whitwell</hi> to conſider, who deny the perfect life of Chriſt to be brought forth in his people here upon earth, and manifeſted in their mortal fleſh by a ceaſing from ſin. And to all others whom it may concern.</head>
            <p>BE it known unto you all who name the name of Chriſt, and would be accounted Chriſtians, this is it that Chriſt the Son of the living God and Saviour of mankind requireth of you all, <hi>To depart from iniquity, ſin, and all ungodlineſs, and return to him who ſaves his people from their ſins;</hi> who is come to judge all fleſh, raiſing up his true and faithful witneſs in all conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which ſhews unto every man upon the face of the whole earth what is ſin, iniquity, and ungodlineſs, to the end they may return to him and repent, and their ſin may be taken away, and their iniquities blotted out, and his <hi>perfect life</hi> brought forth, which doth his will on earth, as it is done in heaven; who witneſs his kingdom come in great power &amp; glory, which is not of this world, therefore the world ſeeth it not, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36. but is ſpiritual, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the carnal, which ſtands in outward obſervations; Lo here, lo there, where men are doing their own wills, and that which is right in their own eyes, there the will of God is not known, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172131:2"/>which ſanctification is wrought and witneſſed to perfection. Now all the world from the head to the tayl, Kings, Princes, Rulers, Magiſtrates, Idol-ſhepherds, falſe prophets, prieſts and people all being out from the pure light of Chriſt in their conſciences, are out of that which gives them the Light of the knowledge of the glorified in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. &amp; 6. and being in darkneſs ſees not the treaſure that is in the earthen veſſels for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot comprehend the Light, neither the excellency of the power of God which is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come to to it; which is Chriſt the power of God, the wiſdom of God, the ſtrength of God, and the life of God. Now all that are ignorant of this power of God by denying it, refuſing to be led and guided thereby, can never ſee nor taſte of the life immortal which dwells in the Light, and in the Light is onely ſeen and revealed. Now all the world being out of the Light, are out of the ſight of the perfect immortal life, pleading for the life they ſee, which is ſinful and mortal, and not the life of God: for the pure life is hid from the adulterous eye, and ſo it appeareth by Chriſts words ſpeaking to the ungodly children of darkneſs, who ſhall anſwer, ſaying, <hi>When ſaw we thee an hungry, or thirſty, or a ſtranger, or naked, or ſick, or in priſon and did not miniſter unto thee,</hi> Matth. 25.44. So here all may ſee that they that live in ſin, and plead for it term of life, are all blind, not one that could ſee the perfect life of the Son of God, and brethren of Chriſt; but on the contrary, beat, perſecute, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, and deſpitefully uſed them, as the ſame generation doth at this day, being all from the Light, denying it, are all blind, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and impriſoning the ſons of God as evil-doers: For when the Lord Jeſus himſelf appeared in fleſh upon the earth, not one of that generation could ſee him to be a perfect man; but the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their learning, Scribes, Phariſees, Rulers, Prieſts and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all blind, ſaying, he was a ſinner, and had a divel, and deceived the people, but were all lyers and falſe accuſers: This was the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of evil-doers which juſtified themſelves, ſaying that God was their father, whiles they were doing the divels work; as the ſame generation doth at this day, who owns his name, but denys his nature; calling themſelves Chriſtians, but perſecute his life, where it is made manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the divel. <hi>Have the workers of iniquity no knowledge, who eat up my people as they eat bread,</hi> Pſal. 14.4. Nay, they being from the light of Chriſt, that which gives the true knowledge of God, how can they know him, or his Son, or his ſervants? <hi>No man knoweth the Son but the Father, neither knoweth any man the Father ſave the Son, and he to whom the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172131:2"/>Son will reveal him,</hi> Mat. 11.27. here you may plainly ſee there is no true knowledge of God but by the revelation of the Son; <hi>The Father by the call of his grace which appeareth to all men, bringeth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all that are obedient to his heavenly call, by the revelation of his Son in them, and the Son being revealed within leadeth to the Father, which by his grace revealed him.</hi> This grace is a ſpiritual free-gift that is come upon all men, though all receive it not, nor believe it, for many turn from it into wantonneſs, that is their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not that it is not come, but becauſe men love it not. Where that which brings ſalvation is not received nor known, how can ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be witneſſed? therefore ſaith the world it is not to be here, but hereafter, putting the day of ſalvation far off, which the Lord hath brought nigh. Here the day of the Son of man is not known; but thoſe that hear his voice know his day, and in his Light ſee it, and rejoice in God their Saviour, the Gentiles light, and Iſrael's glory which is ſpiritual. Mark, the Gentiles Light is Iſraels glory, which every true Iſraelite witneſſeth to be ſpiritual: and are not all thoſe blind Prieſts and falſe Prophets, that turn people from from the free-gift of God, Iſraels ſpiritual glory, the Gentiles Light, the Son of God, and Saviour of the world. Now all that are turned from the ſpiritual gift, the Light of the Son of God which ſhines in the conſcience, to give the knowledge of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, are in darkneſs, conſulting with fleſh and blood, the imaginations of their own hearts, which can never reveal the Son of God within, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16 17. for he was firſt revealed to <hi>Peter</hi> within, before he could confeſs him without; and <hi>John</hi> was in the ſpirit when he ſaw thoſe great myſterie in the Revelations; and it was the Spirit that ſpake to the Churches, and they that have a ſpiritual ear open, do hear what the Spirit ſaith; and he onely hath an ear to hear that is turned to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Spirit which is given to him to profit withal, and the manifeſtation is given to every man, <hi>They have ears, but they hear not; eyes, but they ſee not; and a meaſure, or manifeſtation of the Spirit, but they profit not; therefore are they unprofitable ſervants, which are to be caſt into utter darkneſs, becauſe they loved it, and hated the light, and the manifeſtation of the Spirit which thewed them the deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo chuſing darkneſs rather then light, it juſtly became their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Therefore all you profeſſors who are pleading with the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the world, for darkneſs and the deeds thereof, I warn you all from the Spirit of the living God that you ceaſe from ſo doing, and own his Light, a free-gift which will lead you, if you obey it, to Repentance, and give you power to put off the deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to put on the armor of Light, which is able to ſave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you from the power of darkneſs, and give you victory over
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172131:3"/>hell and death, that you may witneſs the glorious liberty and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the ſons of God, and have an inheritance into the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal kingdom with all the children of Light and heirs of heaven: but on the contrary, if you go on in oppoſition againſt the Light which reproves you in ſecret, and ſhews you the deeds of darkneſs which you live in, and plead for term of life; then ſhal darkneſs be your inheritance, and the reward of evil-doers your portion: remember you were warned in your life-time, and the truth of God declared intender love to your precious ſouls, which the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in all conſciences ſhall manifeſt, that theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to your everlaſting peace: labour to know them before they be hid from your eies; for yet you have a little time, but you know not how ſoon time ſhall be no more. And be it known unto you all, that if you in the Light of Chriſt wherewith you are inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned come to ſee the truth, and come not to the obedience of it becauſe it is reproached, reviled, deſpiſed, hated, and even with much tyrannie and cruelty perſecuted by the prudent of the world, both Rulers, Prieſts, and people, but deny him who is the Light, the Way, the Truth, and the Life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12. and 12. and 46 and 14.6. or refuſe to confeſs him as your Forefathers did, becauſe they loved the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God: know this from the living God, that that ſhall be your portion, for you have choſen it and have refuſed to ſuffer with the Lord and his choſen people who ſuffer tribulation, and ſhall be brought out with their robes waſhed with the blood of the Lamb, to ſerve him day and night in his temple, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. But he that ſuffereth not with him, ſhal not reign with him; though you may think to come in when you perceive the Lord beginneth to exalt his choſen ones over the nations without, but you ſhall know that your thoughts are vain, for you refuſing to ſuffer with the ſeed, come not to have dominion over the nations within, and ſo the unjuſt bears rule in you over the juſt, which God will not exalt with his Son to rule over men or nations without; for he will not give his glory to another who refuſeth to ſuffer with him; for by ſuffering is our ſalvation made perfect, and the reward is to them that work: but he that refuſeth to go into the Vineyard when the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him, ſhall have his portion with the rebellious, even ſo is the kingdom of heaven: but all thoſe who refuſe to ſuffer with the body, exclude themſelvs from being members, not coming to the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, cannot come to the fellowſhip of his reign: for many ſhall ſtrive to enter, and ſhall not be able: Why? they have left the Croſs behind which is the power of God: for whoſoever followeth him, muſt take up his croſs daily in the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of himſelf and his own will, and the will of God comes thereby
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172131:3"/>to be known and done; and where his will is done, there his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is come, and they onely can ſay, <hi>the Lord omnipotent reigneth:</hi> but where the will of another is done, the kingdom of God is not known; but the prince of the power of darkneſs rules in the hearts of thoſe that do his will, who are the children of diſobedience: and of theſe two ſorts are all people upon the face of the whole earth: and here all may plainly ſee whoſe children they are, the light of Chriſt in their conſciences doth ſhew them whoſe will they do: and if you deal plainly with your own ſouls, you need not doubt whoſe ſervants you are; for his ſervants you are to whom you obey, whether of ſin unto daath, or of obedience unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p>If you will not believe the witneſs of God in your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, nor the teſtimony of the holy men of God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whom will you believe? For the Scriptures ſayth, <hi>Whoſoever abideth in him ſinneth not,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. &amp; 9 &amp; <hi>he that comitteth ſin is of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, ver.</hi> 8. can you believ theſe plain words of Scripture, for whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wreſts them it is for his deſtruction; There is no ſalvation but in Chriſt Jeſus: <hi>Mark,</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, and he that abideth in Chriſt Jeſus, is ſaved: how doth that appear? <hi>He ſinneth not:</hi> Mark, then as long as a man ſinneth he is not ſaved, becauſe he is not in Chriſt Jeſus; for he that committeth ſin is of the Devil, &amp; while he is of the Devil he is not ſaved. Then are all that ſin without ſalvation? Yea, if they abide in it. But did not <hi>David</hi> ſin, and <hi>Peter</hi> ſin, and many others who are Saints in Heaven? Yea they did, but did not abide in it, but repented of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and were ſaved from it, which was recorded for all to beware; for had they abiden in it, ſalvation they had not known; Therefore remember theſe plain words, and let them not ſlip out of your minds continually, ſalvation is not known, but as ſin is departed from; this is truth, and ſhall ſtand for ever. And as ſin is departed from, the perfect life of the Son of God is known and witneſſed, and all that plead for ſin are ſeen not to be of God, but in the ſervice of the Divel: Therefore as you will anſwer it before the Lord, take warning from his Spirit, plead not againſt his kingdom, which ſtands in righteouſneſs and true holineſs: for he hath ſet his Son upon his holy hill, which is becoming a great mountain in the earth, and ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever in the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hills, and all nations ſhall flow unto it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. Therefore ceaſe from that which is evil, and obey the Light within, and then ſhall you be delivered from condemnation; for the way of the Lord is peace to the righteous, but he rewardeth the wicked with ſorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172131:4"/>
So dear people as you tender the ſalvation of your pretious ſoule mind the fear of the Lord, that ſo ye may be preſerved out of the iniquity, and may come to underſtand the things that belong to your everlaſting peace in this day of your viſitation, before they be hid from your eyes; now while the Light reproveth the Lord calleth, and ſuch as turn at his reproof, and anſwer his call, ſhall find mercy, but the Light ſhall be the condemnation of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious: So as one that hath obtained mercy, and taſted how good the Lord is to them that fear him, and think upon his name, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.16, 17. I exhort you all to exerciſe your ſelves in the law of the Lord, which the Scriptures of truth ſay is Light, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. &amp; 23. <hi>For if yee reject the Light, then ye reject the Law of God, and caſt it behind your backs, and with ſuch God is not well pleaſed.</hi> And hearken not to the deceivers, who keep you from the Light of Chriſt Jeſus wherewith he hath enlightned every one of you, and tells you it is natural; whereas you know that ſin is natural &amp; the light in your conſcience is contrary to ſin, and reproveth you for ſin: therefore believe them not that turn you from the light, for they are not Miniſters of Chriſt, his Miniſters turned people from the darkneſs to the light, and from the power of ſatan to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. And ſuch alſo are deceivers who tell you the onely way to come to the knowledge of all truth is by the Scriptures; for the knowledge of all truth is by the Spirit of truth, which is the Light that convinceth you firſt of a truth, and then being obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doth bring to the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaid, <hi>I am the truth,</hi> and his ſpirit leadeth into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. &amp; 16.13. and thoſe Prieſts are deceivers who preach for hire, and thoſe falſe Prophets who divine for money or tythes, ſuch cannot lead you out of the tranſgreſſion, for they are in rhe tranſgreſſion themſelvs; for Chriſt ſaid to his, <hi>Freely yee have received, freoly give;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> made not the Goſpel chargeable; but theſe Prieſts that preach for filthy lucre deceivs the people, and keeps them from believing in the Light, leſt by it they ſhould come to ſee their abominations and deceits, and with the ſpirit of the living God this is ſeen, and in much plainneſs and tender love to your pretious ſouls declared, that the ſimple honeſt hearted amongſt you may be delivered out of the mouths of the lying Prophets and falſe Shepherds, who make merchandiſe of poor ſouls for diſhoneſt gain, and filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, and if you put not into their mouths they prepare war againſt you; but the time is near they ſhall gape wide but little ſhall come into their mouths; when none ſhall buy their merchandiſe any more, it being known to be deceit, and the refuge of lies, and all that come to witneſs the teaching of the Lord know it to be truth: therefore we bear our teſtimony againſt them and all other in their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172131:4"/>nature, though got into a higher profeſſion, but at one in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whoſe deceit is the greater, and to ſuch I ſay, What do you profeſs? do you profeſs the life of Chriſt and cannot ceaſe from ſin, but plead for it term of life, as ſome of you do, and poſitively maintain: Is this your profeſſion? then wo is your portion ye hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, profeſſing one life, and living another; or elſe will you ſay there is ſin in the life of Chriſt, or ſeparate him and his life, which you cannot; for his life is to do the will of his Father, and the Son of God cannot be ſeparated from the will of his Father, but from ſinners he is, and ſin ſeparates from God, and ſo it doth you, who plead for it, and live in it from the life of Chriſt: But if thou ſayeſt I am a believer, what doſt thou thou believe? doſt thou believe, as many of you who are called believers do, that is, that they ſhall not be freed from ſin ſo long as they are in the body? If this be thy faith, it is like to be ſo unto thee; then if thou be freed at all it muſt be by thy account when thou art out of the body, that is a freedom, but not from hell; from the act of ſin, becauſe thou canſt ſin no longer but not from the guilt and condemnation <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. &amp; 10. becauſe there is no place for repentance: this is not the freedom of the children of God, for their freedom is by the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.36. which is a perfect freedom indeed from the committing of ſin: but thou that committeſt ſin term of life art in bondage, and a ſervant of ſin, and being a ſervant of ſin, art not redeemed from the power of Satan, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. nor out of the vain converſation: but the true believers come to the purifying of the ſoul in obeying the truth, which makes free, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.32. through the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. and obedience is required in a mans life time, and not to be put off till the ſoul departs from the body: for he that ſleights the day of his viſitation cannot if he would, then it is hid from his eyes, though he may ſeek it carefully with tears, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did before his death, but could not find it, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.17. therefore take heed you ſleight not your day, in hearkning to ſuch who plead for ſin term of life: for in the name and fear of the Lord I warn you to depart from ſuch in tender love and pity to your ſouls, which have been fed a long time with words, but never came to taſte of the bread of life that ſatisfieth the ſoul: but as many as come to taſte of that bread, and feel the Word near in the heart, their ſouls loaths the Prieſts husks, and can feed no more on their chaff, nor ſit one hour to hear them tell their dreams: but when we walked in darkneſs and knew not the light, but follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe blind guides, and were one with them in their deceit, we loved them as well as you, pleaded for them and their deceit, not knowing what we did, for we in that eſtate knew no other way, no other truth, no other life, and thought as you do now, there was
<pb facs="tcp:172131:5"/>no other; but when the Lord viſited us, and ſent his meſſengers who came in the power of the ſpirit of life, and declared the word of the Lord, it reached the witneſſe of God in our conſciences, to which witneſs giving heed, it inlightned our underſtandings, and the body of ſin was ſeen and felt: then, <hi>O wretched man! What shall I do to be ſaved from this body of ſin and death?</hi> Then was the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel which is the power of God known and preached, ſaying, Fear God, and give glory to him, for the hour of his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come: then was the voice of the juſt uttered &amp; heard with judgment upon the head of the unjuſt: then the fleſh trembled, the earth quaked, the rocks rent, the mountains removed, the graves opened, the dead raiſed to life, the captive priſoners came forth, ſalvation known, and the true worſhip of God ſet up, which is in the ſpirit, and in the truth: This is the ſtrait gate that leads to life, and few there be that find it. Now the new and living way is known and witneſſed, and they that walk therein, though fools upon the worlds account, do not err; for it is the way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, wherein the ranſomed &amp; redeemed ones of the Lord walk, who are returned and come to Sion the city of the living God, into which no unclean or imperfect thing can enter the heavenly Jeruſalem; which cometh down from heaven, wherin dwelleth this new birth, the regenerate and new-born babes which ſin not, with ſongs of everlaſting joy upon their heads, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8, 9, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. Now the living praiſes the living God, and true honour and glory, everlaſting praiſes and thanks is given to him who lives for evermore, <hi>Halelujah: He that hath an ear let him hear what the Spirit ſaith to him that overcometh,</hi> mark, <hi>[overcometh] will I give to eat, but not to him that is overcome; for of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame is he brought into bondage:</hi> and here is your ſtate who live in ſin and plead for it term of life, and believe you cannot overcome it in this life, and ſo are ſervants to it: and all in this ſtate have no right to eat of the tree of life which is in the midſt of the paradice of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. But bleſſed and for ever bleſſed are they that do his commands, that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the city, <hi>Rev</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. If here all that live in ſin, and plead for it term of life, are ſhut out with the dogs, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. All that enter this city muſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this work of Regeneration, every man in his own order, and according to his meaſure; and for the everlaſting good of all that cannot witneſs this work, do the miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus labour night and day warning every one every where to repent and turn to the light of Chriſt, which ſhews them all that ever they did, and alſo what they ſhall do, and here the true Meſſiah is found.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Chalfout</hi> in the County of Buckingham <date>the 5th. of the 12. mon. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This was I moved from the Spirit of the Lord to write as a teſtimony &amp; warning to you all, who deny the juſt &amp; perfect one to reign in you, and are pleading for ſin term of life, from one who is a true lover of peace truth, &amp; righteouſneſs where or in whomſoever it appeareth,</hi> Rich. Bradly</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172131:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
